[Music]
what we learned from the tobacco
experience wrote two preeminent public
health scholars is how powerfully
profits can motivate even
at the cost of millions of lives
and unspeakable suffering
big tobacco played dirty and millions
died
how similar is big food i've talked
about how big food has used the same
tobacco industry playbook what about
using the anti-tobacco playbook to
counter the obesity crisis tobacco is
one of our great public health victories
the share of adults who smoke declined
from 42 percent in 1965 down to just 15
by 2016.
that's about 5 out of 12 down to less
than 2 out of 12.
thanks to the decline cigarettes now
only kill about a half million americans
every year whereas our diet now kills
tens of thousands more
currently the leading cause of death in
america
is the american diet
might we be able to use the same
strategies that were so successful in
the battle against big tobacco
it may be no coincidence that three of
the most cost-effective policy
interventions against obesity seem to be
taken straight from the tobacco wars
first
taxes on unhealthy products
front of pack labeling and a restriction
on advertising to children
excise taxes on cigarettes has been
cited as the single most effective
weapon in slashing smoking rates a 25
cents per pack tax to help deal with
some of the societal costs of smoking
was associated with as much as a nine
percent decrease in smoking rates the
world health organization has estimated
that a 70 global increase in the price
could prevent up to a quarter of all
tobacco-related deaths worldwide
extending taxes on alcohol and tobacco
to foodstuffs was proposed by none other
than adam smith in the 1776 wealth of
nations sugar rum and tobacco are
commodities which are nowhere
necessities of life which have become
objects of almost universal consumption
which are therefore extremely proper
subjects of taxation
people have the right to smoke and drink
and eat fattening foods the logic goes
but perhaps they should help defray some
of the publicly funded medical costs
that result
well if that's the case why not tax
obese people directly
taxing people based on their weight was
proposed at least as far back as 1904 in
the british medical journal a kind of
pounds for pounds strategy actually only
up to seven shillings and six pence per
pound
this was not only to recompense public
coffers but nudge behavioral change
attacks on fat read the proposal would
also have the excellent effect on the
health of the nation by bringing about a
reform of unwholesome habits of eating
and drinking
even a penny per ounce tax on sugar
sweetened beverages could bring in more
than a billion dollars a year in states
like texas and california a 10 tax on
fattening foods on the national level
could yield a half a trillion dollars
over 10 years even if it was combined
with a subsidy that lowered the cost of
fruits and vegetables by 10 percent it
would be expected to net hundreds of
billions of dollars
but would it actually change people's
habits
even a small price differential about 10
between leaded and unleaded gas was able
to shift the entire auto industry away
from lead
could it also shift americans to apples
from apple pie
a systematic review of available
evidence suggests that dietary financial
incentives and disincentives work the
cheaper you make fruits and vegetables
the more people say they'd buy and the
more you tax on healthy foods the lower
consumption drops based on this kind of
modeling a tax on saturated fat found
mostly in
fatty meat dairy and junk could
potentially save thousands of lives a
year
but wouldn't such attacks
disproportionately affect the poor
yes in that we would expect them to
benefit the most it's like cigarette
taxes the classic tobacco industry
argument is that cigarette taxes are
unfair and regressive burdening the poor
the most to which the public health
community responded cancer is unfair
cancer disproportionately burdens the
poor so taxes would be expected to
affect the greatest health gains for the
least well-off
the fact that tobacco when she fought
tooth and nail against cigarette taxes
everything from inventing front groups
to overtly buying off politicians
suggests that taxes can indeed shift
consumption patterns but much of the
evidence on changing food behaviors has
not been based on real life data
you can put people through fancy 3d
supermarket simulators and discover that
a 25 discount of fruits and veggies
appears to boost produce purchasing by
the same amount up to about two pounds a
week but virtual vegetables don't
actually do you any good does this work
out in the real world apparently so
south africa's largest private health
insurers started offering up to 25 cash
back on healthy food purchases to
hundreds of thousands of households up
to the u.s equivalent of
799 dollars per month
why would they give money away because
it apparently works increasing
consumption of fruits and vegetables and
whole grains while at the same time
decreasing the consumption of foods high
in added salt sugar and fat including
processed meats and fast food
why not just pay people to lose weight
directly a systematic review found 11
out of 12 studies on financial
incentives for weight loss described
positive results the one that failed to
find a benefit of direct monetary
inducements was only offering two
dollars and 80 cents a day
with kids you can get away with just a
nickel or a sticker to get them to
choose dried fruit over a cookie as an
after-school snack though
as soon as the enticements ended so did
the change in behavior
even if the incentives have to be made
permanent they might still pay for
themselves in the u.s every dollar spent
taxing processed foods or milk might net
an estimated two dollars in healthcare
cost savings every dollar spent making
vegetables cheaper could net three
dollars and subsidizing whole grains
might offer more than a thousand percent
return on our investment even at one
percent decrease in the average price of
all fruits and vegetables might prevent
nearly 10 000 heart attacks and strokes
every year
what about taxes though which tend to be
less popular than subsidies in europe a
number of countries have instituted
taxes on sugary or salty foods but
denmark was the first to introduce a tax
on saturated fat
it only took agribusiness about a year
to squash it demonstrating how weak
public health professionals can be when
trying to tackle corporate power this
was chalked up to the enormous imbalance
between the political influence exerted
by the public health community compared
to the industry's lobbying might
[Music]
you